we have two ways to implement a graph in code
in this video
we're going to talk about the first approach
and we'll look at the second approach
in the next video
one way to represent the edges in the graph is
using a matrix
or a two dimensional array
using this matrix we can see how nodes are connected
so for every known
in our graph we're gonna have a row and a column
if two notes are connected
we mark their intersection with a one or a true
so here we can see that john is connected with mary
bob and alice
this is what we call the adjacent c matrix
it's fairly easy to implement
all we need as a two dimensional era
but the problem with this approach
is the amount of space we need to allocate for this
matrix if you have n notes
our space complexity is gonna be n squared
that can grow very fast
for example if you have 1000 notes
our matrix is gonna have 1 million entries
the approach we're going to explore in the next video
will solve this problem
but let's continue studying this approach
because it has its own merits
now let's talk about
various operations we need to perform
and their time complexity
if you want to add a note
we have to allocate a new matrix
with one extra row and column
and then copy all the existing items and this matrix
into the new one
how many entries do we have here
n squared so adding a new node
is an expensive operation and runs in o of n squared
now we could optimize this by
pre allocating a large matrix
so we don't have to copy
all these items every time we add a new note
but again this is gonna waste memory
also when talking about graphs
we prefer to express the time complexity
in terms of v which is the number of vertices or
nodes in this graph
as you will see later
the time complexity of certain operations also
depend on the number of edges
so we use v and e instead of n
when we do complex it analysis on graphs
now what about removing a node or verdicts
again we have to allocate a new
smaller metrics and copy items around
so we have all of v squared
what about adding an edge
let's say you want to add an edge
which pin alice and john
first we need to find the index of these notes
we can use a hash table
to store our
note and their indexes in the adjacent symmetrics
so in this hash table
we map our notes
to their indexes in the adjacent symmetrics
if you want to add an edge with van alice and john
you find your indexes using this hash table
that's on all of one operation
once we have the indexes
we can quickly go to the corresponding item in our
matrix and turn it on
so adding an edge is pretty fast
and runs in constant time
what about removing an edge
it's the same as adding an edge
we have to go to a given entry in our matrix
and set it to false
how about checking to see if two notes are connected
you want to see if alice and john are connected
again we look up their indexes
and read the value of the corresponding
entry in our matrix
this is an o of one operation
another operation when it frequently is
finding all the notes adjacent or
directly connected to a note
that means the neighboring notes in this matrix
how can we find the neighbors of alice
first we have to use our hash table
to find the index of alice and our matrix
now I need to look at every item in this row
to find the connected notes
how many items do we have in this row
that is equal to the number of notes or vertices
so finding the neighbors of a note runs in o of v
and that means
if you have 1 million people or notes in this graph
and john is connected with only three people
we have to check the connection
between john and all the other 1 million people
just to discover his three connections
so overall
the adjacent c matrix requires a fair amount of space
but performs well
if they need to add
remove or quickly the existence of an edge
finding the neighbors of a given note is a bit slow
and runs in linear time
adding and removing a note are
the slowest operations and
run in quadratic time
so they're suitable if you know ahead of time
how many notes you're gonna need
and you're not gonna add or remove notes often
in the next video we're gonna look at
another approach for
representing a graph